In online lefty spaces, I often came
across this term called shock therapy,
especially at the start of the Russian
invasion of Ukraine. According to
members of these communities, the
invasion of Ukraine is basically the
West's fault. After Western countries
aggressively joined a defensive alliance
so they don't get invaded by Russia. I
wonder why they would be worried about
that. Russia got deeply upset, so upset
that they had no choice but to invade
Ukraine because NATO, a defensive
alliance whose European members up until
recently have been chronically
underfunded and comically disorganized,
was somehow a threat to the world's
largest nuclear power whose military is
otherwise the best, the toughest, the
biggest, the baddest. Thousands of
battle-hardened Russian war machines
ready to destroy the over-engineered,
over-complicated, flimsy NATO tanks if
need be. But they somehow feel
threatened by NATO at the same time. One
could say for these people, tankies,
NATO is both strong and weak at the same
time.
Oh, hold on. I actually forgot to
explain what a tankie is. A tankie is
basically an authoritarian leftist. In
the middle of the 20th century, when the
Soviet Union cracked down on the
Hungarian Revolution in 1956, there was
a big schism in leftism across the
globe. Basically, some people were like,
"Oh, well, that's pretty screwed up for
the Soviets to invade a country that
wants to break away from them. That
looks and sounds kind of like
imperialism." But then some others were
like, "Hell yeah, we fully support this,
actually. We are fully in favor of the
Soviets rolling tanks into other
countries should they try to break
away." And so, because of that, people
started calling them tankies.
>> [music]
>> And debates with these people usually
went the exact same way. "NATO is a
threat to Russia." Was there a danger of
NATO invading Russia, a nuclear power?
"Uh, NATO promised to not expand and
then it did." Was NATO about to invade
Russia? "The West FBI, CIA." Was NATO
about to invade Russia?
Oh, shock therapy. Shock therapy.
Tankies couldn't shut up about it when
it came to the war in Ukraine. Russia
was subjected to shock [snorts] therapy
when the evil West and its capitalists
descended upon the helpless Russians
reeling from the loss of their empire, I
mean, their socialist project. They
forced Russia to enact austerity. They
forced Russia to sell off state property
into private hands for small change.
This ruined Russia and its people. And
so now their anger and distrust against
the West is fully understandable.
Therefore, Russia is completely
justified in its invasion of Ukraine.
Western puppet, NATO outpost, CIA, die.
This sounds rather silly, but this
really is the core of the argument. The
West is bad. In fact, it's the source of
everything wrong in the world and the
reason why all these countries calling
themselves communist or socialist keep
failing. It's all because of the West,
naturally. The root of all evil. In
fact, the West is so satanic, it's such
an axiomatic evil that anyone defining
themselves against the West becomes
almost automatically good. Therefore,
Russia is justified in its attempted
conquest of Ukraine. China is justified
in its coming conquest of Taiwan. Cuba
might have political prisoners and might
be a dictatorship, but my god, look at
how skilled their doctors are. The
Soviet Union was democratic. North Korea
is a secret workers' paradise. You think
I'm joking, but these people are
legitimately this far gone. You know
what else is gone?
Your online personal data after seeing
this. Because the best way to clean it
up is today's sponsor, DeleteMe. We live
in an era where our own data is
increasingly being used against us.
Algorithms build ad profiles out of it,
and governments can of course use it to
track you. Your data can also leak
somewhere, like from a vibe-coded
platform with more holes than Swiss
cheese. Therefore, the safest choice is
to just not have your superfluous data
scattered online. DeleteMe helps remove
your personal data by scanning hundreds
of data broker websites, which collect
personal data, including yours. Then,
DeleteMe will request their removal to
help reduce your digital footprint. A
week later, they'll send you a privacy
report listing out all the things that
they found and removed. Of course,
they'll scan those places later on to
make sure that your data doesn't surface
again somewhere else. Do not let your
personal data fall into the wrong hands.
Get 20% off DeleteMe consumer plans by
going to joindeleteme.com/adam20
and use the promo code adam20 during
checkout. That's joindeleteme.com/adam20
promo code adam20. Thank you for
checking out DeleteMe.
>> Adam Something is a proto-fascist,
pseudo-leftist, and European YouTuber.
In spite of him sometimes espousing
socialist economics and being critical
of anarcho-capitalism and Elon Musk, he
nonetheless is highly supportive of the
neoliberal imperialist European Union
and the NATO. He rejects the right of
self-determination for the people in
Eastern Ukraine, openly promotes
anti-communist propaganda, and supports
imperialist neoliberal politicians in
the EU.
>> The most notorious figurehead of online
tankies is none other than Hasan [__]
a political streamer who's a strange
amalgamation of a political activist and
an e-boy celebrity. Basically, he wants
to be a champion of leftism and an
upper-class Californian socialite at the
same time. The two are not mutually
exclusive, but past a point it just gets
cringey. I am a West Coast millionaire
streaming from my mansion, and I also
support Russia and China in their
conquest of Ukraine and Taiwan,
respectively. Workers of the world.
Also, let me interview a Houthi rebel, a
member of a terrorist group engaged in
attacking civilian cargo ships, human
trafficking, recruiting over 10,000
child soldiers, and more. To these
people, Hasan will pose banger questions
such as
>> What does he think about the fact that
American media keeps claiming that the
reasons as to why the Yemeni militias
are are intercepting vessels is for
completely oblivious reasons like uh
belligerent reasons and not for
Palestine. They don't talk about that at
all here. How does he feel about that?
>> And also compares them to the
protagonist of the anime One Piece.
>> Does he know what One Piece is?
>> He said Luffy?
>> Yeah, he said he's he's been watching it
since he was a kid.
>> [laughter]
>> The whole way!
>> Yeah.
>> That's sick. Yes. Yes. That's fire. And
that's so fire. Oh my god. We think the
Houthis Ansar Allah is doing what Luffy
would do. You should tell him that.
>> Oh, fine. The Houthi stuff was cringe,
but Hasan doesn't support Russia or
China. Yes, he [__] does.
>> Exhibit A. Hasanabi is not allowed to
meaningfully criticize Russia. On
stream, he calls for peace by saying how
both sides have suffered enough. The
injuries on both sides are grave.
Therefore, let's just all stop and make
peace. For whatever reason, he
consistently avoids emphasizing the fact
that all this is happening due to
Russia.
>> Throw the question marks all you want. I
don't give a [__] about the Ukrainian
constitution. I don't give a [__] about
the Ukrainian like border sovereignty
that some of you dumbasses are [__]
talking about like you're you're like a
three-percenter but for Ukraine, okay?
It's so stupid. Crimea is not the same
as Kiev, however. Crimea is not the same
as the rest of Ukraine, however. Eastern
Ukrainian territories have a lot of
[__] Russian people living in them
because Ukraine and just like Crimea and
much of the rest of the [__] country
was a part of Russia. Was a part of the
USSR until not that long ago, okay?
People's parents were alive back then.
So obviously, there's a lot of [__]
Russian people living there.
>> And when it comes to Crimea, which
Russia annexed in 2014, when asked who
it should belong to, Hasan says, "You
>> feeling bad about the Crimean annexation
does not change the reality of the
Crimean annexation being a completely
justifiable [__] act by the Russian
government, okay? So that's it.
That's fine. And Hitler invaded
countries based on Germanic ties the
first. Yeah, dude. Talk to me when he's
[__] throwing Ukrainians in a in a in
a [__]
What are you talking about? Talk to me
when he's throwing Ukrainians in a
concentration camp, OKAY? HITLER WASN'T
[__] BAD BECAUSE HE DECIDED TO INVADE
AUSTRIA. HE WAS BAD BECAUSE HE WAS
[__] KILLING JEWS. OKAY? THAT WAS THE
PROBLEM. HE WASN'T LIKE HE WASN'T LIKE,
"OH, YEAH, we're going to [__] annex
territory with like Germanic people in
it." THAT WASN'T THE MAIN PROBLEM WITH
HITLER, I think. That was LIKE MAYBE
EIGHTH DOWN THE LINE.
>> AND the tankies in his audience are
like, "Hell yeah, brother. Ukraine is
pro-West now, and the West is Satan.
Therefore, we are against the West.
Therefore, we are against Ukraine." But,
it gets worse. Exhibit B, China is about
to invade Taiwan. But, the people of
Taiwan do do not wish to be part of
mainland China. So, who does Taiwan get
to be its own country?
>> Hassan?
>> How do we feel about Taiwan, Hassan? Are
we is it China or not China?
>> That's the American policy. Whatever the
American policy is, whatever the
American perspective is.
>> You really won't [music] say?
>> No, I'm I'm I'm saying it. It's a one
It's one one country, two systems, you
know?
>> No, it's [music] not. It's two different
countries.
>> Really?
>> Taiwan and China.
>> Is that according to American foreign
policy
>> No, what's your opinion?
>> Wait, hold on. I'm going to put Xi
Jinping behind Hassan pointing a gun at
his head. Trust me, it'll make so much
sense.
>> How do we feel about Taiwan, Hassan?
>> Uh one country, two systems, you know?
>> [music]
>> No, it's not. It's two different
countries.
>> Really?
>> Okay, so I was going to move on from
this clip, but instead, let's just
analyze it a bit just for fun. Let's
just assume that Hassan has a handler
who's aligned with the Chinese Communist
Party. From this handler, Hassan gets a
list of things he is not allowed to
publicly say or support. One of them
being that Taiwan should be an
independent country and separate from
China. And so, Ethan Klein asks him
directly, "Is Taiwan China or is it
not?" And so, Hassan suddenly has a
problem. Since he is not allowed to say
that Taiwan should be independent. Even
when Ethan specifically asks for
Hassan's personal opinion, he refuses to
state it because he's not allowed to.
Therefore, he says,
>> What's your opinion? Taiwan independent?
>> My opinion on Taiwan is that Taiwan is
uh
the the the Chinese
concept of Taiwan
should remain uh in the hands of the
people in Taiwan who believe
>> who for the
for the record, for the most part, just
believe to not disrupt the ongoing uh
the ongoing relations uh with China.
>> careful?
>> The Chinese concept of Taiwan should be
in the hands of the people who do not
want to disrupt relations with China.
Yeah, great. See, this is what I mean.
He's just not allowed to share an
opinion counter to the CCP. At the
beginning, he deliberately had to stress
the Chinese concept of Taiwan. AKA, hey
CCP, I'm not talking about independent
Taiwan, which is a forbidden topic. I'm
talking about your idea of Taiwan,
meaning a province of mainland China.
Hasan is stammering and [__] up here
because apparently he hasn't prepared
for such a question in advance. So, he
has to quickly improvise even though
he's bad at it. Trying to not come off
as a Chinese propagandist while also
sounding pro-CCP enough so that his
handlers don't reprimand him.
>> Should Taiwan be a country?
>> Uh the Chinese concept of Taiwan should
be in the hands of the people who do not
want to disrupt relations with China.
>> Taiwan is already independent. That's
what I'm saying. People don't want a
formal declaration just because they
don't want a [__] war. But they I'm
they're not wanting to be Hong Kong and
get be real like consumed by the Chinese
party.
>> They don't want to be Hong Kong? What's
what what happened in Hong Kong?
>> He's also not allowed to criticize the
CCP's socio-economic policies. Check out
this clip of Chinese streamers cooped up
under a bridge in a rich area because in
China you get recommended streams based
on location. So, these streamers are
literally camping out under a bridge
hoping that a local rich person will
check out their stream and donate money
to them. This is both incredibly sad and
very dystopian. The inhumanity of having
to camp out under a bridge to beg for
money from rich people is quite medieval
even when done with high-tech streaming
gear. So, what does Hasan think about
this?
>> I have a to say about this.
Okay, number one.
China has like local streams, I guess,
so they go to like wealthy
neighborhoods.
But more importantly,
like people are like, "Oh, this is so
dystopian. This is so dystopian." It's
like,
dog, how do they have 5G underground?
Like, that's the only thing I care about
right now. How? How are they literally
under a bridge
and they got like straight bars down
there? What is happening? What have they
done in China that we do not have?
>> can't criticize China. He's just not
allowed to. This is incredible. In
addition to all this, it's kind of weird
that after years of railing against US
police behavior and increasing
surveillance, when Chinese police
confiscate his phone at a public event
to see if he'd made any anti-government
posts, he plays it off like this.
>> The flag raising ceremony that we went
to is not a thing that white people
normally go to, right? It's not It's not
normally It's not normally something
that white people attend, right? [music]
And uh I assume that they are probably
extra attentive and extra careful about
people coming uh to to, you know, do
some [__] [__] Cuz like, by and large,
especially like the government is aware
of like how they are perceived or or how
much like uh you know, anti-Chinese
propaganda exists out there. And I think
the older people are also aware of it as
well, but I think the younger
populations in China are, ironically
enough, less aware. Like, the younger
normies are are less aware of the the
animosity that exists, which shouldn't
exist at all, obviously, but
unfortunately does. And it's almost
entirely one-sided, entirely uh designed
by uh America.
>> So, right. Western police are a bunch of
authoritarian jarheads, but Chinese
police confiscating his phone at a
public event to see if he could
criticize the government is just
understandable, bro. He's just not
allowed to criticize Chinese police. But
even if Hasan may or may not be a CCP
propaganda asset, why is he lukewarm on
the Ukraine issue? Why can't he just
say, "Yeah, [__] Russia. Go Ukraine.
Crimea is Ukrainian." Hasan is the
biggest tankie figure, but there are
thousands of other tankie content
creators out there saying similar
things. In the case of Russia versus
Ukraine, it's the aforementioned casting
of Russia as a victim of the diabolical
West, while also claiming that its
masculine battle-hardened armies could
easily overwhelm and destroy the West.
Part of this collective brain rot
mythology is the idea that Russia had
been subjected to shock therapy by the
evil West. And so they broke her, made
her people suffer, ruined her economy,
and so on. But is it actually true?
There is a short answer and a long
answer. The short answer, [__] no. The
long answer is a bit longer. The Soviet
Union occupies a special place in the
brains of delusional online lefties. It
had the hammer and sickle on its coat of
arms and claimed to be building towards
communism, therefore they're good. This
is the emotional foundation of their
beliefs. In their minds, the USSR was a
robust workers guided democracy bravely
standing as the bullwark against the
corrupting influence of Western capital,
except it wasn't and it wasn't. The
Soviet Union, despite starting out as
something of a utopian project, had very
quickly morphed into
Russian imperialism, aka the usual. It's
just like that old joke. Soviet workers
are trying to build tractors at the
factory, but by the time the thing
reaches the end of the assembly line, it
just always happens to be a tank. Or in
the case of the USSR, a full on
dictatorship focused on constant
territorial expansion in all directions
crushing all nations beneath their
boots. Oh, but how can I say that after
all they did like constantly expanding
their territory in all directions
crushing all nations beneath their
boots. My favorite autistic power move
is when tankies claim that the Soviet
Union was democratic. [music] It [__]
wasn't. They did have a parliament
called the Supreme Soviet whose members
were elected by the people and which
supposedly ran the show. The Supreme
Soviet also met two to three times a
year. Now you might be thinking, that's
awfully little for an organization
that's supposed to run the USSR, and
you'd be correct. Compared to
parliaments of even smaller countries
that are in session through the whole
year. In an actual democracy, the people
elect representatives of different
parties into a parliament which then
appoint a prime minister or a president
and send their officials ministers to
the different segments of the state.
Exceptions are the judges and the like
who should be independent. The Soviet
model on the other hand is sort of two
hierarchies on top of each other. The
upper hierarchy is the party. That's
your general secretary, politburo,
central committee, and so on. And this
upper hierarchy controls the lower
hierarchy, which is the presidium, the
supreme soviet, and the council of
ministers, which ratify done decisions
and send people to various leadership
positions like state enterprises,
ministries, and so on. So, in a western
democracy, it goes people, parliament,
government. In the USSR, it was party,
parliament, government. And rest [music]
assured, there was only one party.
People could of course always found
their own independent parties or workers
unions, only they would get disappeared.
This is a great way to short-circuit a
tankie's brain, by the way. Ask them
what would happen if a Chinese person
wanted to found an independent workers
union. The response you'll get will
probably be, "Oh, but there's already a
state-backed workers union. Nobody would
want that. They are just happy with the
current arrangement." That being a
single centralized workers union
controlled by the party. Anything to
avoid the real answer, which is they
won't found one because they would get
[__] disappeared. In some sense, the
main purpose for the Chinese
government's existence is to stop the
formation of independent workers unions.
>> Where ex-communists are still in power,
they are mostly the most efficient
agents of the most ruthless neoliberal
global capitalism. You know what I mean.
If you want to be successful capitalists
today, don't go to Western Europe. Go to
China, where, as every Chinese will tell
you, the main function, almost, of the
Communist Party is to prevent the
formation of an independent working
movement trade unions to keep workers
under control.
>> Oh, hey, that's what I said. Hey, check
this out. Ballot paper from the 1949
Hungarian People's Republic elections
under Soviet occupation. Notice how
there is just one party, called the
Hungarian Independence People's Front,
which was an umbrella organization of
the Hungarian Communist Party that
swallowed all other parties that
previously existed, whose leaders were
now all killed, exiled, or disappeared.
Down there by the one single circle, it
says those who vote against the party
cross out the circle with two lines.
That's right. Submitting an empty ballot
meant that you voted in support. The
Hungarian Independence People's Front
therefore got an astounding 95.6%
of the votes with a voter turnout of
94.7%.
Yay democracy. In 1954 the Hungarian
Independence People's Front would become
the Patriotic People's Front. Up until
1970 only they were allowed to nominate
candidates for elections. From 1970 on
the general public was also allowed to
run meaning anyone could become a
candidate except the entire process was
supervised by the Patriotic People's
Front. And then the 1983 new election
law stipulated that anyone running
against the Patriotic People's Front
must sign a legal declaration that they
fully accept the party program
of the Patriotic People's Front.
>> [music]
>> Great. So we went from only the party is
allowed to run to oh sure you can run
but the party still controls everything
to you can run but you have to do what
the party tells you. This system was
essentially the USSR Red Smog. A
parliament for show, a fake [__]
democracy, the people's everything.
Meanwhile the average person had
essentially no political control over
their lives as all decisions that
actually mattered were made by a group
of powerful and influential unelected
geriatrics sitting around a horribly
expensive table. The USSR and its vassal
states like Hungary were basically state
capitalist oligarchies where the people
owned everything and yet directors of
say large state enterprises appointed by
the party somehow enjoyed the exact same
power and privileges as a Western
capitalist CEO including being driven
around in large black luxury limousines.
Here's a fun tidbit from famous
Hungarian comedian Geza Hofi from 1973
talking briefly about his experience in
the Red Star Tractor Factory where he
was supposed to perform. Basically the
audience was rude so he got up and left
for which the factory's director
reported him.
>> So, yeah, the USSR's leadership became
another box standard ruling class called
Nomenklatura, driving around in their
black limousines, wielding power and
influence in virtually the same way as
their western capitalist counterparts
with some minor caveats for the sake of
optics. Oh, I'm not an evil capitalist.
I don't own the factory. The people own
the factory. I just happen to control
every single aspect of it and
financially benefit from the workers'
production. So, you know, this was an
established rigid oligarchy and in the
case of the USSR one equipped with a
massive military and the most nuclear
warheads on the planet. The idea that
the West or the IMF could order these
people around even post-collapse is
laughable. The West did not impose shock
therapy on Russia. It was the end of
their imperial economic model, so now
they had to change and fast by joining
the global economic system and it wasn't
going to be painless. But at the end of
the day, all that happened was that a
new clique from the exact same center of
power took over the exact same power
structures. For example, Vagit
Alekperov, USSR Deputy Minister of the
Oil and Gas Industry, became the CEO of
Lukoil. Rem Vyakhirev, USSR First Deputy
Minister of the Gas Industry, became the
CEO of Gazprom. And this enterprising
KGB agent first became the mayor of St.
Petersburg, then president for life. At
the end of the day, Russia has never had
a revolution, just a changing of the
guard. The best example of this is the
port of St. Petersburg where three
massive flags are flown next to each
other. The modern Russian flag, the USSR
flag, and the Russian Imperial flag.
Three systems that were on paper
diametrically opposed to each other. In
reality, they weren't. It was the same
thing under three different flags. What
a perfect representation of the history
of the Russian state. So, what went
wrong? How did all these so-called
communist states turn into
dictatorships? Friend of the channel,
local political activist and co-op
member Matyash, has an answer for us.
Communism isn't just about eliminating
private capital from production. The
structure of labor has to change because
if it doesn't, it will inevitably
maintain the inequality produced by
rigid hierarchical systems. If one
person, for whatever reason, gains a
higher status compared to others, this
leads to inequalities. This can stem
from multiple sources. Historically, the
first status difference came from
spiritual values, from the privilege of
having certain knowledge. This helped
solidify the system of shamans, later
priests, and philosopher kings. They
knew how the gods work, therefore they
have to be in charge, otherwise the
world will descend into chaos. As our
economic systems evolved, such as
through agriculture, currency,
stockpiling methods, mathematics, and so
on, a new status difference emerged
stemming from material wealth. If you
have more land, a bigger workshop, more
ships, and so on, then you can produce
and/or move more goods, therefore you
become more important, therefore more
influential. In our capitalist world,
our tech billionaires are simultaneously
wealthy and are spiritual leaders to
those who follow them. If you grind hard
enough in your garage, you can also be
part of the Silicon Valley dream. At
least that's the vibe they're selling.
And if you think that's not true, then
you are an envious and lazy individual.
With that, let's take a look at Stalin
and Hitler. Stalin practically ruled
over everything because as the general
secretary of the Soviet Union, the state
had to be organized based on his word.
Obviously, the organizing part was not
performed by him, but by his
high-ranking officials, but he was the
one appointing them, just like how
nobody could lead a kolkhoz, a
collective farm, without the consent of
the party apparatus. Next to all that,
faith must be kept in the idea that if
the proletariat grinds hard enough, then
we will reach socialism. And if you
disagree, you are a class traitor.
Things were similar with Hitler. Hitler
was in charge of the Nazi party, which
was in charge of who could get ahead and
maintain the same illusion that if you
grind hard enough, you'll bring about an
earthly Aryan paradise. And if you don't
cooperate, you must be neutralized. The
packaging is different, but there are
some relevant common themes. The
decisions of one person can affect
millions. As an authoritarian leader
with nearly total power, you decide who
gets ahead and who gets exiled. Your
power in the material world is complete.
Cults are built around various imagining
utopias. The main motivation is the
reaching of some ideal paradise
corresponding to the values of the era.
And in this pursuit, the leader doubles
as a high priest guiding you towards it.
The us versus them mentality. Anyone
daring to question the material and
spiritual powers that be is a deviant.
Hierarchy remains in all facets of life.
It doesn't matter if it's the party, the
CEO, or the king appointing the prole
superior. Proles will have no say in
anything. Proles do not own their labor.
If you work for the party in a factory
and the party works in the same way as a
modern company's board of directors, the
prole does not own anything.
Authoritarian systems will inevitably
lead to paranoia and inequality and will
maintain hierarchies that are
diametrically opposed to socialism, the
egalitarian world without classes. If we
simply nationalize everything while
maintaining the same hierarchies, we are
not creating a socialist system, but a
despotic state corporation. And while it
cannot be denied that compared to
capitalist systems, redistribution in
the USSR increased like healthcare,
Comecon blocks, and so on, power still
remained in the hands of a narrow elite
who wanted to uniformize the proletariat
along a single ideology. The proletariat
was not an active participant in the
formation of this ideology, rather its
victim. And to this day, we see the same
thing in both private oligarchs, like in
the US or in the brittosphere, and in
state oligarchs, like in Russia and now
formerly, hopefully in Hungary, in
addition to the state corporation called
China. Karl Marx was a vehement critic
of fetishization and alienation. The
ideological objectives of authoritarian
systems are the given system's fetishes.
For capitalism, it's growth. For the
USSR system, it was the success of the
planned economy. For fascism, it's the
reaching of some ethnically pure and
honorable world of Aryan greatness. But,
these fetishes alienate workers from
their work and their communities.
Because in such an environment, they are
not working for the benefit of their
fellow human beings, but for the given
fetish. Therefore, the problems of
ordinary workers cannot be solved by
repackaging the existing structure and
touching it up here and there. If the
structure stays the same, nothing will
change. The Hungarian Revolution of 1956
against the Soviet structure did not
happen by accident. It was started by
factory workers and students, meaning
those who have not yet alienated
themselves from the real world that
surrounded them. Moreover, in its
beginning phases, the uprising was not
against communism, but against the cult
of personality and totalitarian control.
After the Hungarian Communist Party took
over and ended democracy, workers did
not become freer. Even the peasantry had
less, despite the mechanization of
agriculture. The intellectual class was
strangled by censorship and constant
surveillance. 1956 was a revolution of
democratic socialism against the
Soviets, and Soviets crushed it, just
like how the CIA destroyed the Chilean
president Allende's Cybersyn project,
which was an attempt at a digitalized
democratic socialist system. Socialism
does not start with a change of despot.
The real point of socialism is giving
back workers control over their work.
That way, we free people from demands
generated above them. The five-year
plan, marketing [__] a pure and
honorable homeland, and so on. The basis
of this is the democratization of the
workplace, for which exists a
functioning model called cooperatives.
Cooperatives are not some sweet, syrupy,
Care Bear hippie communes, but
workplaces. Their goal, however, is not
the servicing of some higher objective
like constant growth, five-year plan, or
an Aryan Disneyland, but to meet the
needs of their workers, meaning
livelihood and some extra. And this is
done by selling various goods and
services. The process of work is decided
and enforced democratically. This form
of work is therefore free of
fetishization, because you are providing
goods and services in exchange for your
livelihood, not some abstract goal
handed down to you from above, from
people you've never met. You don't work
for the five-year plan, GDP, or some
vague utopia, but because you want to
live well and someone else needs the
service you provide. And this system
cannot be reached in an authoritarian
caste system like the USSR was or like
China is today. Once we get to the point
where entrepreneurs, family businesses,
and cooperatives dominate the economy,
we will then be able to say that finally
democracy has grown out both its legs
and can start moving forward.
In closing, I'd like to give you a
real-life example of this. The vast
mutual aid system of the Hungarian
peasantry called Kolkhoz. Back then,
meaning 100 years ago, in the
countryside, peasants made larger
projects happen in cooperation. If
something big needed to be built or some
difficult task had to be performed,
people pitched in with the expectation
that someone else would also help them
if needed. Assisting others was an
expectation, not a favor. So, the
community was basically in a circle of
assistance that with each other. Who did
what and how much was recorded of
informal ledger. The Smith family helped
the Johnson family build a shed, so the
Johnsons helped the Smiths during
harvest, and so on. This was later
formalized into local exchange trading
systems or LETS. With this, simple serfs
created the foundation for cooperatives
without having to chew through thousands
of pages of theory or to resurrect Lenin
or something. And the best example of
this was the Hangya Cooperative in
Hungary, translating to "ant", which
started out with 50,000 crowns worth of
capital, the equivalent of 120 hectares
of land, equaling to the land property
of around 200 families, basically the
wealth of a single village. In 10 years,
their revenue grew to 12 million crowns
before the crowns' hyperinflation. And
by 1940, the cooperative had 2,000
member organizations, 700,000 members,
30 canning factories, 20 industrial
sites, and more than 400 stores. It was
all in the hands of the peasantry, run
in a democratic cooperative model.
However, in 1945, the Hungarian
Communist Party nationalized it all
without any compensation, essentially
stealing the property of the peasantry,
thus destroying what couldn't be
destroyed by the Habsburgs, the Nazis,
and two world wars. Go [__] figure.
Thank you for watching, and if you like
my content, please consider becoming a
patron or a channel member here on
YouTube. Best regards to Hassan Abdi CCP
handlers, and best of luck to all of you
in this heatwave. And I'll be seeing you
next time.